welcome everyone back to trim tab space
camp
uh we're here today with daniel
schmucktenberger
trimtab space camp as you all know is
this
opportunity for all of us to think big
and to explore the world around us and
understand
the wider context within which we all
live
we're looking at different defense
making frameworks
we've learned about ecology and gaian
systems and rapid prototyping
in this course and leave it to daniel to
go meta
and teach us about sense making itself
daniel is a good friend and
a student of buckminster fullers started
reading him before he could read
actually uh
his parents would read him synergetics
as bedtime stories
um and he's kind of a
protege of fuller's amongst others and
just uh i i look to you daniel as
a source of wisdom and uh
confidant and advisor for the
buckminster fuller institute
and just such an honor to have you here
today thank you so much for making the
time amidst this
wild global crisis uh and thank you for
all the response work that you've been
doing
for this i really appreciate it very
happy to be here
i remember when you and i first talked
about this type of course happening
for uh bucky fuller institute where
people could learn good
sense making tools and be able to apply
them so i'm just really delighted this
happening now i think it's a great
service yeah
they met a great time so we're going to
explore scents making today
uh could you kick us off with just
telling us some of the
core principles of sense making and how
we can maybe apply that to this
global crisis it's a funny way to see a
conversation like principles of sense
making and the reason we use a term like
sense making is how do we make sense of
the world and reality that we live in
which is kind of a uh
common vernacular for epistemology
how do we go about knowing things and
what is the basis for appropriate belief
in something and this obviously a
not only the basis of the philosophy of
science which is how do we go about
knowing objective things about the
objective world
but all of philosophy
the epistemics of whatever it is that
we're claiming is true about
anything what is our basis of our truth
claim and so
someone can easily study this field for
their whole life and scratch the surface
of all the good thinking that has been
done
and our basis for right action in the
world to be effective at anything is
going to be our basis of understanding
the nature of the world
and the nature of being able to consider
what the effect of a particular action
are going to be
so uh overview of sentence making 101
like we're
what i hope we can do is
um share a few principles that are a
valuable start
to just add something to the picture
that can also inspire people if they're
interested in terms of where they can go
further
um and maybe be able to show the
application of those to things that are
currently trending questions with regard
to this
you know covet 19 global crisis and the
attendance out of
world issues that are happening
so i'm going to assume
also that the basic philosophy of
science
and kind of basic
karl popper uh sensibilities and
kind of understanding of logical
fallacies and critical thinking is at
least somewhat familiar
and if that's not true then
take a look at those terms that i said
and at least go read the wikipedia page
on them
um logical fallacies critical thinking
philosophy of science
popper those would be starting places
those are by no means an
adequate frame for sense making but they
are common
valuable frames good starting places so
i'm going to kind of assume those and
build on there
uh if i use terms that you think would
be unfamiliar please
stop me and we'll unpack them
so
the difference between science and
epistemology writ large just to kind of
say it is
uh science is an epis the method of
science is an epistemology it is a
process of knowing
about the objective world we find
ourselves in meaning objects that can be
measured
and then where we can do repetition on
measurement and then be able to abstract
patterns from those
but measurable things are third-person
things right we can all
measure something independently get the
same type of measurement and then be
able to
so measurable and replicable science
exists within the domain of the
measurable and replicable
if you imagine we have a two by two
matrix of things that are measurable and
unmeasurable there are a lot of
things that are real and are
unmeasurable like an emotion you can
measure
a neural correlate and you can't get
anywhere close to actually measuring all
the things that are happening we don't
even begin to understand how to do that
we can do very rough
you know qeg whatever kind of stuff you
can't measure in motion it's a first
person thing you measure third person
things
uh you can't measure the inside of a
black hole you can mathematically infer
stuff you can't measure things that are
below the scale of measurability
there's a lot of things that are real
that are unmeasurable which means
they're formally outside of the domain
of science but that doesn't mean that we
can't
that any claim about them is equally
true right there are still methods
of uh sense-making
that are going to be more reliable than
others
and then replicable there are certain
things that are measurable but not
replicable because
it's not a control kind of situation
where we can replicate it
so formally the thing that we call
science the processes of science
exists within one of four quadrants
in which the real includes all of those
so when we talk about sense making we're
including all of it
and uh so science is necessary
but not sufficient and it ends up
becoming actually bad epistemology when
you collapse
the real to the objective right because
then
subjective is not real if you make real
an objective synonymous
subjective is also real but it's not
measurable and you can't do
repeatability on the non-measurable
things right
um and
intersubjective things are also not
subjective
right that's that's actually a whole
different quadrant of
uh things and even some things that are
objective or not
properly measurable um or where there's
causation but there's no
way to assess necessary and sufficient
causation in a formal way there's nexus
causation like in
complexities we have to apply different
kinds of principles so
um and this is when you hear people talk
about the problems of reductionism right
trying to reduce all of the real to the
objective
trying to reduce complex situations to a
subset of the variables and that can be
very useful reductionism is super useful
but it also has limits and so it would
be bad sensemaking
to use reductionism without
understanding its limits it would also
be bad since making to
reject reductionism in a kind of
overly sweeping sense
now when we're looking at social
situations
there's and trying to make sense of
politics and economics and whatever
there's a lot of things where we won't
really be able to measure what's going
on there's information that our
company secrets and trademarks and
patents that are intentionally
kept classified or obscured by
governments there's stuff that we
haven't figured out yet and yet there's
still
consequence to what's happening now and
we want to figure some stuff out that we
don't have the ability to do
the appropriate formal science on even
if it was in the domain of science and
why are certain agents doing the things
they are has to do with intent which is
outside of measurability we can only
measure the effects of it and try to
infer
so sense making of what's actually going
on
and how do we know and how do we get
enough confidence to inform right action
and when do we not have enough
confidence to inform right action and
how do we have
a clear basis for what our confidence
margin is and what our confidence margin
for right action based on the
consequentiality of the situation what
should it be
this is like kind of how you start to
think about what the topics that sense
making is addressing
are i'll actually speak about confidence
for a moment
one of the things oh well actually come
one step back
the essence if you wanted to say there
was an essence
the essence of good sense making
is earnestness in the desire to
understand
what's happening and in earnestness it
both wants to know what is rather than
wants to believe something in particular
and an earnestness that is willing to do
the work that it takes
to actually come to understand that
rather than jump to premature beliefs
because that is comforting or allows you
to be part of an in-group or seem
knowledgeable or whatever else
kind of brings us back to a couple of
things we've learned both in ecology and
in
in rapid prototyping just like the
importance of
humility and curiosity you know of
of not being attached being maybe
committed to something
but not attached to what it may be um
in the case of rapid prototyping and
then in the case of ecology yeah just
being
kind of humble and curious about the
world around you and seeing it
in more of that kind of dynamic as well
right right
so curiosity and humility and
earnestness these words all kind of go
together here right
and um so it was
a very nice definition of science
eddington gave that science is the
earnest endeavor to put into
order the facts and experience so what
are the facts of experience how do we
know
and like what are we what am i
experiencing what are others
experiencing can i trust that they're
recording the facts of their experience
you know in an adequate way and how do
we put into order some kind of
sensibility of that
um so if earnestness and like
depth of curiosity is the kind of
essence of science and epistemology in
general
then bias would be the enemy of it
and bias can come from lots of sources
it can come from wanting to be part of
an in-group that believes a thing so you
where it's costly not to believe that
things you'll be excommunicated from
your religion or
seen as a conspiracy theorist or a
status quo or whatever it is that your
particular in-group would happen to see
as bad
that's going to create a source of bias
if you want to be seen as in the know
because you have particular kind of ego
identifications or you want the previous
thing that you did your phd on
and got famous for to keep being right
even though new stuff is coming out that
might suggest
otherwise right ego stuff can obviously
be a source of i want this to seem true
whether it actually is true or not
financial interest is probably the main
thing that messes science up
because somebody's funding the science
and typically
that funding is coming from some
existing pool of money that made the
money by doing something that makes
money
that is going to fund stuff that makes
it more money so it is not interested
in things that are not going to make
money it's interested in things it
probably will
and that means that either self dealing
right
self dealing and you know even if
so it's totally possible that someone is
doing science in a way where they're
actually
doing authentically bad science because
of financial interest they are
um hiding data and whatever but it's
also possible that someone does
quote-unquote good science
but that where the preponderance of
evidence is misleading because they're
only looking at the parts of the whole
picture
that have profitability so if i look at
pharmaceuticals for instance
and the research into healthcare
doctors currently because the regulatory
landscape in the u.s aren't allowed to
prescribe something
if it is not fda approved to prescribe
that thing
fda approval process requires phase 3
clinical trials that cost most of a
billion dollars
who's going to pay for that well a
pharma company can pay for it if they
can make that money back
and make enough money back so to be able
to make that much money you have to look
at a patented thing because otherwise i
put in
the research money i put in the billion
dollars and then i'm selling something
competing on the margins with other
people that can
make the thing at the same cost and
didn't have the upfront billion dollars
so i've got to be able to recoup that
money by having a much higher price that
nobody can undercut me
so we can only patent synthetic
molecules for the most part
not things that are in plants or
nutrients or whatever so those things
are just never going to get the same
kind of research funding so then you'll
have a preponderance of evidence that
says
these things are more effective than
these things but it was because they
were
and it's not even necessarily that each
study was bad but it's it's not well
distributed the distribution of what's
being studied in the distribution of
reality don't match
right and um so that's another place
where bias is going to
uh be able to affect and mess up sense
making so because of that i would say
that we have less real science in the
world than i would like to see and we
have a lot more of the r
d arm of capitalism and
this becomes one of the things that for
individuals trying to make sense of the
world when you're even if you're
reading scientific papers
trying to make sense of all of the
papers in a space together trying to
make sense of the biases of the authors
trying to make sense of the bias
associated with the funding
looking at the methodology itself these
are all things that are worth factoring
when trying to make sense of something
i was going to say something about
confidence and certainty
so it's very
one of the major sources of bias is
emotional
biases do we talk about cognitive bias a
lot in science and that there are
like all of these logical fallacies or
cognitive bias but a lot of them come
from
emotional or identity or existential or
social kind of needs
where believing something actually feels
like it is meeting some
need or way for me to live so i have a
basis other than just knowing what's
true to want to believe something in
particular
so a lot of people who are seeking
security
conflate that the way to get security is
certainty about the nature of reality
and so they will seek excessive levels
of certainty with an insufficient
process for gaining it because they
actually have a certainty bias because
they're unsafe if they don't have that
right or
something like that that's an example
it's not exhaustive
so a fundamentalist religion would be a
classic example
where i am utterly certain about the
absolute nature of reality the name of
god
uh what happens after you die and all
this kind of stuff and it's like really
um that whole idea only
came about not that many thousands of
years ago and before that that
people were just as certain about other
and uh that you know that
that particular god name had never been
proposed and um
but there is the you can see in the face
of the uncertainty and the unknown of
death
if someone is not friends with the
unknown
if they're not friends with uncertainty
and they have then
where they can't see they can project
scariness into that space
then they want to be certain and so they
want to
have faith even if it's not
epistemically grounded
it's actually very interesting people's
fear of dark
and it's like why is it that i'm more
afraid of the exact same environment
when i just can't see it
than when i could when it's the same
environment with the same agents in it
and i'm not even somewhere that has
nocturnal animals or whatever like what
maybe sometimes that's warranted but a
lot of times that's not warranted right
so where does that come from well
if i can see i know there's nothing bad
if i can't then my mind starts
projecting stuff in there people have
this of dark water of deep water
you know where they can't see in death
right so
and unknown in general so it's very easy
to have a bias towards certainty and now
that can be expressed through
people who are quote unquote using
scientific
ideas just as much as it can religious
ones
so there are people who are quoting
science
but what you can see is they don't think
of science as a process of knowing they
think of it as a body of knowledge
and that there are these things called
facts and that they're totally well
known and that
those people who understand it are right
and other people are
not just wrong but stupid and um and
uh and they you'll notice that the bias
and the nature of their communication is
to always have pretty high certainty
even it's just even if it's just very
high certainty that other people who are
presenting something that doesn't look
like the science they want are certainly
wrong
and so you're like oh they've got that
same bias going
and they're plugging in a science
uh set of languages rather than a
religious set
now on the same side people can have a
bias towards uncertainty
but these are still biases so this is
classically what happened with
post-modernism
right and post-modernism said science
actually
claimed some that it shouldn't have
claimed it actually had the wrong
epistemology and it had bias going and
this was specifically in the social
sciences
where uh whatever victorian white
men were looking at the racial
superiority of men or
the white race or looking for monogamous
pair bonding in nature because of
victorian ideals when they did zoology
or whatever you're like oh
this is actually a pretty significant
confirmation bias messing up the thing
that we're calling science but being
accepted scientific ideals so then there
became this idea
that science was just the same as all
the other
i'm giving an extreme example so forgive
me obviously
foucault and daradah were not stupid and
they didn't say this but a lot of the
people who don't read them all that well
make this kind of generalization that
uh that there is no truth
there is no absolute truth there is no
way of knowing what is more true and
that anyone who claims to have
a more more access to or a
valid process of truth is just some form
of imperialism
and that because science wasn't
spreading industrialism at the same time
that empires were using it to suppress
the lower class and
kill indigenous people and ruin the
environment that those are somehow
conflated and that then
all perspectives on reality are equally
valid and we need to listen to them all
equally and there are no valid truth
claims
this is gibberish right because
recognizing that social science is
subject to bias in a particular way
where you have extraordinarily high
complexity and a high basis for bias is
very different than say
physical chemistry that does not conform
to it like that's very very simple
and uh doesn't have the same kind of
bias being admitted so
um and also then the fact that some
people did social science badly doesn't
mean that it can't be done more
earnestly and better
so it doesn't mean does it mean that we
always want to be looking at bias
yes in science that we shouldn't
consider science unbiased yes
but does it mean that all truth claims
are equally valid no
the social science thing is the um
acronym weird weird populations white
educated industrialized rich and
democratic
there's a narrative a you know a
rightfully so narrative that a lot of
the social scientists
uh sciences have been studied on weird
populations those you know people who
are kind of readily available
in uh industrialized college settings
um so that's one thing that people have
been pointing to more and more and i
think it's
it's really important right now for us
to kind of just point out like where
where are we exhibiting different you
know
racist or colonialist perspectives
but yeah also not throwing out the baby
with the bathwater and
i think that differentiation you made of
science being
a methodology rather than kind of like
the set of um
truth that's like already known um
is really critical you know as we're
putting out the design science
you know decade uh as buckminster fuller
institute like getting people to kind of
blend in
the design thinking with um
all that we can um yeah glean
and understanding the world through
science uh it's really helpful to have
that
differentiation so when you think about
the social sciences here
and what we said in the beginning about
the measurable and repeatable
i can measure a chemical pretty well i
can do different types of measurements i
can use
microscopy and spectrometry and whatever
and
and then contrast that and a lot of
other people independently can
and uh the physical properties the
chemical properties of it will conform
pretty well
i can't measure what someone feels
or really the nature and nuance and
complexity of what they think or the
sense of their relationships or their
motives are
or whole populations or how those change
i can observe
certain things about the output
behaviorally
but then i have to infer a whole lot and
so
the total complexity of social science
is
way more complex way more variables and
there's way more that i can't directly
measure right it is out it's not
third person it's first person and
second person
and so that was absolutely an
overstepping
of the idea of what would fit into the
rigorous domain of science and what the
nature of the truth claims could be
um so while it's true so
yes it's true that there's a lot of
stuff that we have excessive certainty
of that we shouldn't it's also true that
we can overcompensate and pretend that
we don't have
uh the certainty on some things that we
should and
uh that there are not better epistemic
processes even if none are perfect for
coming to
confidence in something so this question
of what is
for a particular topic in that domain
what is the appropriate epistemic
process
to come to us to relative confidence
why do we think that it's that as
opposed to something else
and what are the axioms that we're
drawing upon and how do those reify
themselves
and um
what is an appropriate level of
confidence and what is an appropriate
process to come to that level of
confidence
to inform certain kinds of action
right those are all kind of important
questions now i'm
i'm getting into this a little bit more
formally than i thought we would and
um to get into the more probably daily
practical stuff we'll get there in a
moment and it might go beyond the course
of what we can do in this uh
short time but i wanted to say this
thing about certainty and uncertainty
is a mature relationship to certainty
uh there's a rabbi friend of mine that
actually first told me this
so it came from that background but a
mature relationship to certainty is that
we're comfortable having certainty where
it is warranted
knowing that it's never 100 but there
might be 95 or 99
based on the total amount of data that
we have relative to the total situation
and we're also comfortable in
uncertainty because if like the
postmodernist
we're scared of certainty or
uncomfortable with it or like on the
other side we're uncomfortable with
uncertainty both of those are biases
that won't actually have us just think
clearly
so we want to be friends with
uncertainty knowing that the
unknown and actually the unknowable is a
very large infinity
and then we also want to endeavor
earnestly to gain the certainties that
inform
appropriate right action responsible
right action where we can actually take
responsibility to affect the things that
we care about in the world
so i don't want to be attached to that
what i think is right but i do want to
be attached to understanding reality as
clearly as i can so that i can act as
effectively in service of
the good so if i am working towards
helping hunger
and i work really diligently and
earnestly and make no progress and more
people are getting hungry i want to be
able to say that i'm failing
right like i it's it's very important
and then i want to be able to say i
should do something different
rather than continue doing that thing
because i actually am result oriented
here
not just processor i actually care about
the people getting fed
or the chronovirus getting solved and so
i want
to make sure that the pro that my
understanding of what's going on
that informs what i think would be
effective that informs the
things that i try that then i re test to
see are they working is actually working
okay that's all very basic but it's
still worth kind of framing up
um i think we can get into how does
what are good tools of episemics but
probably
i think the place where maybe the most
value can be harvested the fastest is
what are the most common places where
people mess up
like how do you you're probably
sense making badly if yeah i think that
would be helpful
especially in this moment as we are all
trying to
make sense of this crisis and what it
means
and you know a lot of people in this
course looking to like
what is the opening that's being
provided by all of this right and
wanting to step into that without being
tone deaf too
i think it's a theme that a lot of us
are looking into
um and part of that is just making sense
of what's happening
yeah making the tragedy worse
okay so with regard to
that you know the tragedy worse is there
an opening to make it better
the better and worse are not what we'd
normally think of as epistemic
questions they're ethical or existential
right like what is good and what is
bad and but that's absolutely relevant
so there's bias
there and let's speak to it
so there is a bias that i notice
really damaging people's sense making
when it comes to coronavirus and it also
damages their sense making regarding
climate change and existential risk and
kind of risk writ large
i'm going to oversimplify on purpose to
start the topic
and knowing that i am oversimplifying
and we could get into a much
richer discussion of it there are
it's it's easy to have a bias
that we could kind of flatly call a
positivity bias
that doesn't want things to be really
bad
like just doesn't want to believe that
think that can't
be with it doesn't want to feel it and
so wherever their
people are claiming that is bad
they're likely to think that
it's probably alarmists those are
probably people that are catastrophizing
there's probably some good innovation
that's going to come along that will
solve it like they
there's a before even researching it
there is a immediate bias either to be
kind of almost aesthetically repulsed by
it or to move away or to assume it's
probably wrong or probably won't be the
whole story
whereas when evidence comes along and
things are getting better or it's not
that bad there's an
instant resonance before doing a similar
level of sense making it's like oh this
is
look see things are getting better and
there's a kind of positivity bias that i
think is actually
worth having and a kind that isn't worth
having
the kind that biases our assessment of
what is is terrible
the kind that is committed to
understanding what is
very very clearly including all of the
negativities that are current and the
negativities that could be the risks
so that we are empowered to help make
things better and the positivity bias is
that i want
my thought word indeed to all be working
towards making things better which
requires understanding what is
that kind of positivity bias is great
it's not messing up our sense making
it's applying our sense making in an
empowered and constructive way
but i'm not going to be good at making
things better if i'm not seeing what is
clearly
so there is a you know when you think of
the term spiritual bypass but it can be
a psychological bypass or a kind of
epistemic bypass of any kind
it's any
spiritual idea or philosophic idea or
bias
that wants us to not be with the some
pain
right so in the kind of spiritual bypass
whether it's like
well they reincarnated to have they
incarnated to have those lessons or
their soul
chose this or there will be some silver
lining in it or god works in mysterious
ways
it's some way of being able to say i
don't have to feel bad about this thing
that otherwise i would feel really bad
about because i don't feel like i can
hold that
or be with it which
is kind of like a pseudo-sociopathy
right one of the things about sociopaths
is that others can be hurting and they
don't feel bad
which is why they can hurt others and so
any idea that makes us
able to not feel bad in the pre in the
presence of others feeling bad is taking
beliefs that are moving us in the
direction of a sociopathy-like
set of behaviors so
when i'm seeing people who are gasping
for
air and dying in that way and their
family members can't even be with them
on their deathbed because they would get
sick
upset about it right and that it's
unnecessary and they could have
prevented that i'm
super sad for them and i'm
super mad at
the people that are making choices that
they for
poor reasons that could have prevented
it or done a better job
and i don't i wouldn't want to feel any
other way
like there would be something wrong with
me if i didn't feel those feelings it
would mean that i
like i had to be fractured inside
i'm speaking to this because i see this
rampantly
with people latching on to oh there's
this new drug it looks like it's going
to work before there's really good sense
making that we know enough
about the drug because they really want
something that's going to work
oh there's this great new diagnostic
test oh there's this one epidemiologist
that said it's really not that bad
oh look there's this thing that shows
empty hospitals maybe it's really not
that bad
and they'll latch onto that ship before
really studying it but reject the other
which means that they won't be part of
making things better
so this is a very common bias and of
course it goes without saying the exact
opposite bias is also common
which is a catastrophism bias which is
whenever there is something that looks
like it
uh could be that something isn't that
bad or
there might be a solution someone tends
to think that it is probably going to
fail
and when they see anything that looks
like a possible risk they assume it's
probably going to happen
and they emotionally and it's
it's like okay let's say we look at the
situation today where the response to
covet has started to damage the food
supply
that's a huge deal because messing up
the food supply and
wars and riots over food supply and
insufficiencies of food supply whatever
could kill a lot more people than the
virus
and that's a place where our response to
the virus might be much worse
than the virus itself and we it's a big
deal so
is there a big deal when you start
messing up the food supply yes
does that mean that food supply is
already so messed up that it's
inexorable that two billion people are
going to starve no
we can still totally do stuff about it
but there are some people who i've
talked with over the last couple days
who've called me freaking out saying
did you see like there are locusts in
northern africa and the middle east and
crops rotting in india we're losing the
food supply everybody's going to starve
well it's true there are locusts in
northern africa in the middle east
and it's a big deal and crops
are rotting in india
it's not true that 2 billion people are
going to starve it is true that they
and but what's happening is that possib
typically we want to do worst case
scenario forecasting so we can prevent
it
because if you don't know that it could
happen then you don't see what the
escalation pathways are then you can't
prevent it
and but then if we prevent it the people
the positivity bias will say see you
were just catastrophists
for doing that nothing bad really ever
happens all that bad ever happened
it would have happened had we not done
these things it only didn't happen
because we did the worst case scenario
planning and saw what it took to prevent
it
um so i want to do worst case scenario
but know that it's a scenario it's not
that it's already happened and then i
want to see how to prevent it so i want
the positivity to be oriented towards
action
not towards sense making um so does this
make sense on positivity negativity bias
and how they mess up our sense making
mm-hmm
definitely especially where there are
high consequence high pain topics
yeah yeah and it seems like there's just
kind of this through line of
um kind of like the ego getting in the
way
of like people want to have the
the bias towards certainty but a bias
towards certainty kind of shows up in
this way too
intermingled with the positivity and the
catastrophic
bias of just people especially right now
because everything's so up in the air
people just want to have some grinding
you know and so i've seen in myself and
in others
just biased towards okay i want to make
sense of this i want to know
you know what's happening in what order
with what time frame
um and i think something that we've seen
again
in a through line through a lot of what
we're learning is just like the world is
dynamic
it's always shifting change is the only
constant and so how can we
kind of be more comfortable with not
knowing
exactly what's going to happen but be in
that state of
um i'm still widening our view still
having
like facing that with like a deeper
hunger
for knowing as much as that we can yes
and the deeper hunger that is not a
hunger that jumps to false conclusions
because we want them
but it does the hard work that it takes
to actually endeavor
towards so you know i really want to
know
what you were just saying right i really
want to know what's going to happen what
could happen
what the right order of operation should
be how we should tend to think that's
i i'm working on knowing that stuff but
i don't think
that i can scroll my facebook feed and
read for several hours and have a good
sense of those things
um it's kind of like i
want to be buff and i don't want to work
out
that part like it's just not going to
work right this so there is an input
output equation that has to happen
and like being buff or being able to
play the piano like being able to make
sense of a topic takes the work that it
takes
and um so now this brings us to the next
bias
well i can't do that much work because
i'm not an expert in virology or an
epidemiology or an immunology or
a industrial sanitation engineer or
in uh diagnostic
medicine or in the privacy
considerations for contact tracing
or in macroeconomics or in domestic
politics security or in the nature of
what's happening with geopolitical
positioning or in
supply chains of food how the could
i possibly know all that
but there are authorities that know this
so i'm going to defer to the authorities
i'm going to cognitively offload that
complexity
now there is a bias in terms of how
people relate to authority that's
important
and it's similarly oversimplifying
has a by some two directions both of
which are bias which means not clear
which is there are people that tend to
think that
most of the people who are in the
primary authorized positions are
probably trustworthy
which would be a silly thing to think
and other people who assume that they're
always untrustworthy and corrupt
which is also a silly thing to think and
those are very kind of sweeping
generalizations that keep us from
actually doing sense making because
we're not looking at what are they
actually saying what is the track record
of where they've been right and wrong
on this topic so far and historically
and where is there a divergence or a
convergence of opinions of people and
am i biasing towards some of them
because of political association or
because of positivity or negativity bias
or things like that
so can i find virologists
that are saying oh this is not mutating
in a way that's going to have a worse
strain
yes can i find other ones that are
saying oh the next strain is probably
going to be many times worse
yes who are experts so how do i possibly
make sense of this if i'm not a phd
virologist and there are eminent ones
who disagree
you know pretty intensively and
on every topic we can say something like
that right
well you actually can this is the nice
thing is that the
the you have the benefit of being able
to look
at where experts are converging where
they're also diverging and what the
basis of the divergence is
and possibly having less bias than them
because you didn't get a nobel prize
saying this thing where you have an ego
invested in defending this particular
thing and you don't have research grants
that need to believe in this thing
and you haven't had all of your
attention in this one part of the
picture where
this virologist is looking at this this
one's looking at this one's looking at
this you can have an epistemic
flexibility that can look at those and
also look at
what the nature of the bias they might
be running is and try to get some
parallax across those
and so um
but on this one about authoritarian
versus anti-authoritarian bias
this is one of the most common
things that i see that messes up
everyone's sense making
so
there is a meme complex you can see all
over the
facebook say which is i'm tired of
tinfoil hat wearing conspiracy
theorists talking nonsense and armchair
epidemiologists
this is the place for experts if john
hopkins in the cdc say if that's what's
true nobody else should be weighing in
on this would
we should listen to the things they say
and empower the experts on this
and vaccines work and i don't want to
hear anything else about it and
um whatever the authorities think are
appropriate measures are the things that
we should do
right and that everything else is
gruesomely irresponsible
and then of course we also hear this
other meme plex that all of the
authorities were completely corrupt for
various
vested interest purposes and we can't
believe any of them and everything that
they're telling you is false and and i
think both of these are pretty close to
equally gibberish
yeah you know hanlon's razor is a
philosophical razor that's like
don't attribute to malice what can be
adequately
attributed to ignorance yeah and i think
so many of us
you know yeah our trust has been broken
in however many ways
and then we like think you know they are
out to get us
um i think it can be a waste of precious
human brilliance it's a ways of thinking
okay so there's very strong bias in both
directions when it comes to conspiracies
conspiracy are there times where some
people
conspire meaning share information with
each other that they don't publicly
share to advance particular agendas
that if publicly shared wouldn't work
all the time
like that is the nature of the world now
does and so like for every watergate and
enron there's a million of those that
are not
publicly caught but like that's what
machiavelli told everyone to do
that's what sun tzu and the 36
stratagems that's what military theory
and political theory is all about right
how do you
conspire with some in group to advance a
particular agenda in
against out groups and anyone who'd get
in the way of
and when you look at genghis khan and
napoleon alexander the great when you
look at the barbarism of the 12th
century we're genetically those people
still
we have the same brains and the same
hormones like we're not that different
we have just
like we we're more civil in some ways we
also just hide it better
so you know our lovely previous democrat
president we
bombed a lot of civilians to death
in the middle east with the largest
military the world's ever known
um but it wasn't here right and factory
farms are as brutal as
anything has ever been and their mass
scale and most people
contribute to it financially they're
paying other people to do their dirty
wet works for them
and then feeling civilized um
and so we should not wrongly assume that
we are more civilized than we are
and that there is not a ton of
malice or even just
having accepted that that's the nature
of the world and you know
rationalized ladder climbing in politics
we also shouldn't assume
that every time that there's something
that
doesn't make sense that it is
highly coordinated malice because
coordination is actually fairly hard and
very often it is just incompetence and
or the nature of the incentive systems
so assuming any of those things means
you aren't thinking
if you're assuming it's probably
ignorance you aren't thinking and you
aren't paying attention you're bringing
your own bias into it if you're assuming
that the authorities are probably well
intentioned or they're probably not you
are not thinking
and so this is what i want people to
notice in their bias is
what things tend to bother them there
are a lot of people where if it comes
from an authoritative claim they're just
bothered off the bat or if it sounds
conspiratorial they're bothered off the
bat
this is not good sense making or there's
something that's a rule of thumb
like you just mentioned that they take
as if it was almost absolute like they
apply it kind of uh feverishly
what i'm wanting is for people it's like
ecclesiastes a time to kill and a time
to heal and to sew in to reap
there's a time for every epistemic tool
like there's a pla there's a place where
they all
apply and so what you want to do is go
into a situation and say maybe malice is
happening
here maybe
simply incentives and politics are maybe
incompetences maybe it's actually being
handled brilliantly and my overall
assessment of why something handled
brilliantly is wrong
i don't know and i don't know just
because it's an authority or just
because it's a
wealthy person or a whatever or just
because it is part of trump or
you know the people who are against
trump if trump happens to like
hydroxychloroquine
no one should automatically like
hydroxychloroquine more or less because
trump
happened to say it because the fact that
he happened to say it has nothing to
do
with whether it works or not and
obviously trump didn't just pull
hydroxychloroquine out of thin air some
doctors and scientists told him some
data about that now so we should
actually look at the data on that
very closely and carefully
during the obama administration and all
the administration
since nixon washington dc primarily ran
what they called the benign china
hypothesis china's not trying to become
a world empire
and you know free trade with them and
blah blah and
you know we started hearing trump china
china china china and
people being upset that there he was
wanting to do certain kinds of
uh tariffs or trade war type things or
whatever but being concerned about what
the
uh chinese geopolitical agendas were
he was right he was actually right the
benign china hypothesis was gibberish
if you read the hundred year war uh
and you look at the activities of
chinese communist party there's
absolutely global agendas it would be
silly to think otherwise
now he wasn't right out of nowhere he
was right because
bannon and others happened to give him
insight there and it happened to
resonate with
that as just kind of a deal maker kind
of guy when he sat across from them
he probably had the sense of like oh
it feels like
these guys are playing some pretty
serious game that i
some some go game that i don't feel well
set up for
now he's been wrong about a gazillion
things
and so again wanting to over norm that
he's wrong and stupid and evil about
everything or right and the savior on
everything is not thinking
now of course it's fine if i'm trying to
sense make there might be some people
who are right often enough
that i look to them as sources of higher
signal lower noise up front but i still
check
and there might be other people that
even though they've been right a couple
times i assume it's probably low
signal enough that i generally don't
check but i can't
generalize on that in consequential
areas
so hydroxychloroquine i'm going to use
this because
this is a very good example of where
sense making is tricky
where it's consequential
so hydroxychloroquine is a anti-malarial
primarily but it also has antiviral
properties has been used as an antiviral
and is used in rheumatology uh heavily
for
rheumatic conditions it's a drug that's
been used for many decades
very heavily since vietnam the united
states military has put
most u.s soldiers on it before they
deploy to areas that have
malaria as a malarial prophylaxis so
before they go to
every week for the first four years of
my life because they lived in ivory
coast
yeah exactly and um
so we have a pretty enormous amount of
data on the long-term effects and the
safety and the whatever
of hydroxychloroquine is it a totally
benign drug
no it's not vitamin c uh it can
absolutely affect hearts
this thing called the qt interval uh
it's contraindicated with some meds in
some conditions
but do we at least understand the
contraindications in the general safety
profile well especially as a old generic
drug that has been around forever and
been in combination with all the other
drugs and has a generally pretty good
safety profile relative to advanced
coveted infections yes do we have
randomized control trials that show that
it's effective
placebo can you know double-blind
placebo-controlled multi-location type
of thing
no those are slow those take a
long time to do
now those are awesome like randomized
control trials are totally a good
sense-making tool an epistemic tool but
there are a bunch of people who have
been
taught that it is the only tool that
exists to make sense
of pharmacology which is utter nonsense
that means that those people
are not actually making good sense of
the world or thinking they are
they've been drilled in this kind of
uh over norming on one tool because it
happens to be a lovely tool
when we can do it and it also happens to
be the one that the fda wants and so it
also happens to be the one
that you better take if you want a
maximum security position to have your
malpractice not get you in trouble
so this is another source of bias on it
right what is the maximally defensible
position
is also a major thing okay
by the time the randomized control
trials are done
heaps of people will be dead and icus
will be overwhelmed and case fatality
rate will have
spiked precipitously so
should we give people drugs that might
be more dangerous and not effective just
based on
um pendulum dowsing no but
are there ways of making sense of
something to enough degree to
affect some kind of action yes so with
regard to hydroxychloroquine i'll use
this as an example
there were randomized control trials for
it in sars
sarge cove one right
that's meaningful it's a different virus
this a novel virus
but there's a lot of similarities in
mechanisms
there were randomized control trials for
it and other viruses including other
coronaviruses
there have been in vitro trials on that
are
very effective on this one on starzqv2
and there are a lot of non-randomized
control trials but open label trials
ones in china one's in south korea one's
in france the one in new york but then
heaps of doctors that are using it that
are not nothing right they're not
placebo controlled
but they're not nothing now
there are some things that just placebos
don't really affect
right placebos don't do a good job of
healing broken bones
um and so we don't need placebo controls
for things that don't really produce
placebo effects and so placebos don't
kill viruses now
do placebos modulate your immune system
to some degree sure
right but is there an amount of
effectiveness
that placebos have on viral conditions
statistically so you can remove that
statistical artifact and then be able to
still look at
is their uh effect beyond this just
statistical artifact
so that's like a way of saying hey we
can actually kind of make sense
of this here factoring placebo
considerations even if we're not doing
the placebo control trial
um so we
brought a group of doctors together a
group of mds to
work on doing a literature review of
hydroxychloroquine
and by itself and in conjunction with
zinc and azithromycin and doxycycline
and other things like that
and we looked at the mechanistic trials
in vitro trials the animal trials the
current open label trials
previous ones and we were looking at
preponderance of data and looking at
relative benefit to risk
in different populations that's actually
trying to do sense making with all of
the available data
factoring the consequence of action and
inaction now i
don't get malpractice lawsuits for
inaction in the same way i get them for
action so that ends up being a source of
bias and a cya you know cover your ass
kind of way
that is different than just trying to
sense make how do i save the most lives
and so i know doctors many of them who
i've spoke with in the last few days
who gave themselves prescriptions of
hydroxychloroquine for themselves and
their family and said this is absolutely
what i do with myself and my family
based on all the literature but i'm not
allowed to prescribe it at my hospital
because the hospital said we would be
fired for prescribing it because uh for
outpatient treatment because of those
concerns
that hospital policy
i believe is gruesomely negligent and
life-saving
now are we suggesting that people drink
fish bowl cleaner obviously not
are we suggesting that people prescribe
to themselves no
that you don't look at heart conditions
and comorbidities no of course not
what we're saying is should prescribing
physicians who've taken a hippocratic
oath and who are scientifically literate
people
be given emergency authorization to
be able to prescribe as they see fit
based on the current literature and
preponderance of data for life-saving
purposes
yeah i think that's a good emergency
authorization
um where they're not worried about
getting fired or malpractice things
so that they can actually be focused on
doing the right thing here
now again with regard to
hydroxychloroquine
there's pretty good evidence that in
late stage infection it doesn't help
very much
but there are very few antivirals that
help in late
stage infection in the entire corpus of
medicine
and the general rule of thumb with
infection as a whole is treat early
rather than late because once it gets
bad it's much much harder but especially
with viruses is that only
in the very beginning do you have
meaningful chance so
a lot of people know if you get shingles
or if you get herpes a cyclovir can help
if you get to it within 24 hours
at most 48 hours after that we'll do
almost nothing in that time it does a
lot
if you're in late stage aids the
cocktail
antiviral cocktail doesn't help that
much if you're in very early stage it
will prevent disease progression
so if you do a randomized control trial
for
hydroxychloroquine or even the open
label trials
or fda provisional emergency approval
for late stage as an antiviral when
pretty much no antivirals work late
stage
and then you assume what that means
about the drug writ large and factoring
for early stage that would just be silly
that would be going against the
preponderance of knowledge we have about
viral mechanisms and antivirals writ
large
so the randomized control trials should
be for early stage right
which is kind of akin to like how we've
been testing people we've only been
testing
we predominantly have been testing the
very sick rather than
random sampling and so we don't really
have a good idea of what the denominator
is correct
so we do need background random testing
for
epidemiological forecasting and being
able to think about
herd immunity and inoculating with less
virulent forms of the virus and other
things like that
but stand on this one for a moment
so one should we wait for randomized
control trials
to be able to make sense of something no
we should look at the preponderance of
all of the data the risk
and the reward think about different
populations of risk sensitivity
and comorbidities and whatever
differently and be able to actually
apply
all of the sense making we have to the
scenario and know that the sense making
we would do if we had all the time in
the world is different than the sense
making we would do
when there is consequence to inaction
which is why i said we have to have the
right relationship to certainty and
uncertainty on the basis to
come to it factoring the
consequentiality of action and inaction
now would we like to do randomized
control trials to get more knowledge of
course
should we be doing them late stage only
well if we want
let's say i wanted to and i'm not
ascribing malice where it is very likely
ignorance but
if i wanted to do an information warfare
tactic
to prove that trump was wrong in an
idiot or
to make a generic drug like
hydroxychloroquine that nobody can make
much money on seem ineffective so some
patented drug can make a lot of money or
whatever
if i wanted to do that i would set up a
late stage trial that showed that it
wasn't effective and then over
generalize those results across the
board and i would also
set up a late stage trial where the
placebo is vitamin c which one of the
major studies is doing right now where
vitamin c is widely known to be an
effective antiviral and then i get
plausible deniability that i'm doing
good science because it comes from a
prestigious university when what i'm
really doing is info warfare to an
advance an agenda
so um now we start to get into
i struggled through watching this david
ike thing the other day
it was very painful there was
extraordinarily little signal in it not
none but very very little
conspiratorial stuff
that said
so hong kong had almost nobody die
because of good response
and south korea didn't respond quite as
quickly but they responded well
still very few deaths okay well they're
littler
places islands um whatever well germany
is not an island it's not a little place
and their cfr is extremely
low czech republic extremely
vietnam poor
poorer relative country doing great
well some of those asian ones had sars
so they were prepared
czech republic didn't germany didn't um
those are both landlocked they aren't
islands those are you know
democracies not dictatorships
could we just not have responded better
well we allowed 430 000 people to fly
from china since the thing happened to
the united states
because border closing is xenophobic no
it's not we're
closing the border to viruses that
happen to be on people from wherever the
they came from
close the border to them coming from an
european country if that's where they're
coming from
so this is now a place similarly where
if somebody jumps to
the problem is xenophobia or racism
they're not sense making again
we should absolutely shut
borders during pandemics where
viral transmission is like physically
transmitted
you should shut borders between counties
within states where there's very highly
different distributions of it within the
counties to be able to
prevent excessive spread just like you
are we're stopping the
transmission between people and people
even within the same city right
um so is it
possible that all of the profound
getting everything wrong that we have
done
the who until a few weeks ago telling
people not to wear
masks and ppe and whatever that that's
all just stupidity and incompetence well
that would be impressive
it would be impressive is it possible
that there are some agendas where
if things get worse they do better
well if the eu that's already under a
lot of tension
gets more tension because some countries
get in other countries that could
help them aren't helping them because
they only have enough to help themselves
it kind of breaks eu apart so that the
eu can't bring in the eastern european
countries because russia wants the
baltic states would russia have the goal
to do information warfare kinds of
tactics to get the baltic states back
i don't have to say they are doing this
to say everything in the precedent of
unrestricted warfare in the history of
how these things happen
says that they would of course have that
orientation is the way that china would
be trying to do the belt and road
initiative
take advantage of the fact that they're
the only supplier of ppe and on the
other side of this and the
groups will sign the bottom line on
things that have fine print that they
wouldn't have otherwise if they're going
to die at the plague and
you know and similarly if there are
groups that want increased surveillance
capacity
so this why should we trust the
authorities carte blanche
no that would be silly should we assume
that they're all
corrupt and controlled by reptilians no
that would be silly
should we actually try to do sense
making on each specific thing itself
rather than do this over generalized
thing that unfortunately we can't do in
this particular world
of cognitive offloading yes that's what
we have to do
so with hydroxychloroquine we can see
okay late stage versus early stage
is this really a placebo or is this not
a placebo
it randomized control trials are
desirable are they the only thing
uh mechanistic studies other viruses
what can you
tell from another virus to a novel virus
um what degree of certainty would be
needed based on the consequentiality
these are all examples and there's like
a dozen more i haven't got into
of epistemics you would want to think
through to know how to make sense of
this
and that you should favorite ways like
there's
bayesian decision theory like there's
different ways to kind of make sense of
things with probability
and um yeah do you have favorite tools
that you like to use
i'm upset at the idea of favorite tools
each of them it's like i'm going to
build a house with a screwdriver
screwdrivers are awesome
tools that you come back to often all of
them
and for the things they're good at so
network theory
and graph theory are the best things for
the thing that they do and probability
and statistics and different statistical
tools
mathematics in the domain that it's for
computer modeling agent-based modeling
you know machine deep learning on large
data sets
first principles thinking in the place
where first principles thinking applies
bayesian analytics where that applies
you know crowdsourcing versus expert
sourcing um
when do we use induction and deduction
and abduction
favorite tool intellectually is as silly
as
favorite tool to try and fix a car or
build a house
yeah i like wrenches to fix a car
awesome
they talk to screwdrivers and they suck
for welding
and so if someone actually wants to be
able to fix a car you got to have a lot
of tools know how to use them and know
which one to use for which situation
and if someone wants to make sense of
the world same thing and if that seems
like too much
then you should just accept the idea you
probably won't understand the nature of
the reality you live in and be able to
make good choices
yeah so
well within that it kind of like it
helped i mean it brings up people's
biases of like wanting certainty and
wanting
um yeah both positivity and certainty
come up for
in that just like oh can't you just
explain it to me in canada i'll just be
okay
i've been taught over and over again as
like an okay response to the world
well this is the psychology of a child
that wants a parent
to be able to depend upon yeah
um and it's actually interesting
i don't want to over norm here i don't
want to do bad sense make an over normal
topic that is super complex but i will
draw a parallel that has at least some
truth value
the way people related to their parents
as kids often
reflects itself somewhat in the bias
they have towards authorities later
their parents and teachers and whatever
other authorities in childhood
so the people that did better in school
and did better with their parents and
kind of did well with the standard model
more often than the other crew will tend
to think that the standard model is
well and think that the current
authorities are probably trustworthy and
good and the people that didn't do well
at those things
and didn't have trustworthy authorities
are more likely to
have that generalized sense right that's
not an absolute it can come from lots of
other things later life events
but those are interesting things to look
at and it's also interesting where it's
like
i want someone to just reassure me that
everything will be okay
how old is the psychology having that
thought
i don't know what's going on and i feel
scared how old is that okay so now we
need to do therapy
for inner child trauma stuff that is
going to hijack our adult brain being
able to make sense of the world
and that will make us susceptible to
other people being able to
influence us more than they should yeah
and dangerous authorities and whatever
start to come into is they can prey upon
that
yeah and i think one of the root causes
of so many of our
our interdependent crises right now is
that kind of avoidance of
that inner work avoidance of it being
even okay to talk about those things
you know um i mean it seems like there's
a trend towards
you know being okay with therapy or
coaching as kind of like a
therapy like tool that people are
becoming more
um yeah it's just it's
less stigmatized than it once was
people realize that their effective
choice making requires effective
understanding about both the nature of
the world and what the effect of a
particular choice or injunction is going
to be
then wanting to sense make clearly
becomes a very high
goal and once they realize that a lot of
the bad sense making comes from
psychological predispositions biases
that come from those places
then psychological work
actually becomes part of sense making
so do you know as much as i might want
to learn math or statistics or bayesian
analysis i might also want to
be able to do bias assessment and be
able to see where those biases arise
from and clear them
yeah so this moment that we're in
is an opening
for a healing at a lot of different
levels and one of those is i'm finding
as people are in
stressed situations some of their kind
of unaddressed trauma
is arising and i think similarly
kind of like our unaddressed root causes
of
you know what's creating the ecological
crisis
and and climate change and everything um
yeah there's an opening right now for us
to see right like the the true meaning
of apocalypse is
an unveiling of a greater truth that was
that was unapparent before that moment
happened
um so yeah curious to hear what you
think of
kind of all of that incense making and
in this moment
i'm gonna share something that i have to
share a dialectic of things
for it to make sense
so where people notice that there is a
psychological process that seems more
like a child than an adult
psychological process i want to be
reassured i want to be
comforted i don't know what's going on i
want to know that an authority is taking
care of it or can tell me what's true
anything that they do from there will
not help
if they're trying to act on the world if
they're sharing information or whatever
so the only thing they can do from there
is actually respond
to this address their own psychology
until they come to a more empowered
place and then from a more empowered
place try to sense make the world and
then act from clear sense making
don't act from those places um
so i really want to see people showing
up
in a adult way
but the dialectic with that is you can't
just
snap your fingers and get there because
you want to there's work that it takes
if the
if there are unresolved child trauma
type things that keep hijacking you into
that
state pretending that that's not the
case and saying
oh yes i feel very calm and centered and
i'm speaking like an adult i'm freaking
out inside whatever
like then you're just schisming yourself
and so i want to see people showing up
as an adult
and that means i want to see them seeing
where they aren't and doing what it
takes to actually get there rather than
pretend
and where they aren't there i don't want
them to have shame about it but i also
don't want them acting on the world from
that place i want them acting on
themselves
and then i want them acting on the world
when they're in the right place to act
on the world
i want us supporting each other in this
if you see somebody
sharing information and trying to act on
the world from a place that doesn't seem
actually clear that might be propagating
problems
then lovingly try to support them to
recenter
neither add to it nor attack them
because that's not going to help
right just try to lovingly help them
recenter and be open to when others do
that with you
in fact ask for it seeking the counsel
of people who
you consider wise counsel is a sign of
wisdom itself
um now with regard to
traumas coming up to heal right now yes
and this is another thing so i want
people to show up as adults and that
takes whatever it takes
right so people if people are at home
and they have extra free time maybe this
is the time they can be doing
skype therapy sessions and they can be
reading the things and doing the
meditation and doing the journaling that
they've wanted to do
that'd be great we it's either a
solitary confinement or an ostrom
right like it can be this great mental
health crisis where
we get a huge amount of benzo addictions
that just ruin everything
for a long time or a
uh emergence into people going
deeper into their own wholeness together
and with each other
uh now we want to work on which of those
it is for ourself
and with our communities and with the
world as best we can
the same with the educational crisis
this can be the generation of kids that
all got no education for some time and
had upset parents traumatizing the
out of them
at in a small place or where we actually
reinvent schooling in a much better way
in education because we need to so
in all these ways the same with health
care the same with the food security
system the same with our risk prevention
system the same with
macroeconomics it can either get much
worse
or we can use this catalyst to make
things much better to be able to do the
larger macro things we have to be in the
right place to be capacitated to do that
so we work on that first and then the
other and it's somewhat you know
ongoingly back and forth as needed
in addition to i would like people to
show up as adults where it is
possible being able to
show up in a way that is calm
and clear and grounded and not biasing
towards seeing things
as better or worse than they are but
very clearly and then biasing towards
how to make things better effectively
the people who can do that are the
people who will lead the solutions and
other people will look to
but you can't pretend you've got to do
what it takes to actually have that
happen
and this image of the coal pressurizes
into diamonds by
pressure by intensive pressure right or
the steel
becomes hard through the
temperature of the forging process and
the banging on it right
so as there's increased pressure we can
either have it
fracture us or turn the coal into
diamond where we become clearer and more
crystalline and precise and and to have
that as a frame
that as the pressure gets more i
actually go slower
clearer more grounded just even as an
intention
can be helpful
yeah that's really beautiful um
yeah i forget his name bio i think it
depends his last name he says that
times are urgent slow down
um yeah it's
really important and counterintuitive
and
you know um i think yeah just overall
kind of this
this appetite for bias and really
understanding it is
yeah a powerful outcome of this time as
we're all
trying to ground in the healthiest way
possible
u.s special forces has this uh statement
and
there's a lot of versions of this
perennially but
slow is smooth and smooth is fast
and it's not saying go slow when urgent
action is needed it's saying go
fast but mistakes aren't fast mistakes
end up being super super slow doing
doing like you're trying to clean the
kitchen so fast before guests come and
you break glasses and now you gotta
take the time to clean it up and it's
way slower than had you moved a little
bit slower
so you don't want to break right
you don't want to spread misinformation
you don't want to act on this
information
so you got to go slow enough to go
smooth where each step is actually a
right step and gets to build on right
steps
which is actually the very fastest thing
you can possibly do
so i'm actually encouraging people to go
fast but actually fast
which means clear smooth
right yeah
yeah um
wonderful we're we're approaching the
end of our time here
i feel um we covered a lot
of principles and and biases and
just a lot of insight is there anything
else you would offer one thing we're
asking people is are there any
vocabulary terms that people can
insert into their
you know daily or weekly use that would
enable them to kind of
kind of upgrade their their ability to
make sense of the world
there's certain things that you
unfortunately though this is not
absolutely the case the community of
practice that in general looks at
critical thinking and logical fallacies
and they're the ones that look at bias
the most or very very frequently in
terms of cognitive bias
that whole field in my opinion admits a
certain bias
which is kind of funny which is that it
is
biasing towards analysis over synthesis
so it wants to make sure that it's not
having any wrong ideas and it rejects
wrong ideas but it's not necessarily
making sure that the very
partial reductionist ideas are being put
together in
good overarching frameworks which is the
synthesis side
so it there is a need for synthetic
thought and creative thought
as well as very analytic thought and so
the
the tools of critical thinking generally
help you with the analytic thought more
and so those are necessary but they're
not sufficient
and there are places where they're rules
of thumb that are not true they're rules
of thumb
so like the uh
occam's razor right sometimes the thing
that is true actually
is more complicated than you know the
hypothesis than something else
so it's just a general kind of razor
just for those who don't know is like
the simplest solution to something with
the less variables is
more likely to be true yeah and and we
might say that statistically that is
often the case but it also even depends
upon the scenario like
the simple economic models are always
really wrong
and the simple biological models are
always really wrong because the
causation is actually complex so
really depends on the domain so uh in
terms of terms
i think people just going and looking up
epistemology and reading the wikipedia
page or the oxford philosophy
page and just kind of having a basic
sense is good
uh looking up
and then if you want to do the wikipedia
rabbit hole thing
so it'll if it mentions bayesian
analysis take it take a little trip down
there
and maybe go watch a couple youtube
videos on bayesian analysis and on
network theory on
graph theory on statistics on learning
basics
things about statistics on as you're
hearing the terms epidemiology and
virology and immunology so much maybe
just read the wikipedia page to start
like do i know what a virus is do i
actually know what rna is what's the
difference between rna and dna do i i'm
hearing pcr
and serological and immunological do i
know what the words mean
how about i just look up the words that
i'm hearing especially before i use them
yeah um that and i don't have to read a
textbook let's
read a wikipedia page to at least have a
beginning sentence which will actually
help
humble you because you'll realize that
there was much more that you didn't even
know that you didn't know about
and then you'll probably as you know
more actually be more humble in your
presentation than
you knew less and just repeated a word
so
okay in terms of words i would suggest
every word that you're hearing
it seems important that you're tempted
to say again
look it up first yeah
awesome yeah and kind of we ask every
i guess lecturer to come up with an
activity i feel like that could be a
good one is
starting with epistemol uh epistemology
go down a rabbit hole and kind of see
where you go and see what you learn
any other kind of guide posts along the
way as people are going down that
journey that
they can should consider in terms of
doing good sense making
not just starting with the epistemology
page but starting with anything on covid
you're reading or looking at
make a list of all the terms that you
don't know what they mean
fully and go
read about them and then follow those
rabbit holes
um super valuable and just a super
simple thing
we are creating the information ecology
for each other
the epistemic commons for each other and
just like it's not good to throw trash
on the ground and pollute because of
shared space and the effects it's not
good to put trash information out
it pollutes the information ecology so
before you share something
you remember there was this this early
greek
that held his thumb up to the moon
closed one eye and said at arm's length
my thumb exactly blocks out the moon
therefore the moon is the size of my
thumb
and my palm can block out the sun
therefore the sun must be the size of my
palm
and i don't know if that's a true story
it's a story that is told in plushy
sometimes
uh and if you didn't know that depth
perception was a thing
that affected size it's a rational
argument
right where the axiom is that
distance doesn't affect relative
perception of size right it's
not understanding the nature of a visual
cone it's a rational argument that's
gibberish
very easy to have rational arguments
that are gibberish because they have
wrong axioms or missing something
it's entirely possible that you read
something
that makes sense to you because there's
a rational argument
and it makes sense everywhere
that the virus has been bad their 5g was
recently installed
and everywhere there's 5g the virus is
bad oh and
5g just got pushed through oh
well go fact check that first just
look at a map of all the places that 5g
is and then look at a place a map of the
places that
the virus is and see if the claim made
is true before you share it
because it's not in that particular case
and so just because something
sounds compelling and it seems maybe
plausible upon first blush
doesn't mean that it's true and
but if you put it out even if you say
what do you guys think of this
because you didn't want to do the hard
work of making sense of it lots of other
people who don't want to do the hard
work of making sense of it will be
compelled the way that you were and it
starts to affect background thought
you're actually polluting the
information ecology you're throwing
styrofoam
your intellectual styrofoam into the
ocean right
and so just don't do that um
and at least do enough research to see
that it's if something is
probably not grounded and then if you
don't know how to go further
then do an adequate preface i looked
into this here's what i could find
here's what i couldn't find i'm really
trying to figure this out does anyone
have good data on such and such
and then tag the people that you think
are probably the people who might be
able to figure it out
right start smaller instead of polluting
a whole
wider landscape yeah yeah i think that
makes a lot of sense
and just like i think people yeah going
to like primary source
you know just being having an appetite
for doing our own research
i think so many people have become
accustomed to just getting information
from other people who've already done
the synthesis
and kind of going back to a couple
points ago you were saying
there's a lot of a lot of kind of
analysis oriented tools
and not as many synthesis um
tools or rules of thumb or or
yeah work in that realm how can people
kind of balance that out for themselves
so this thing that is often attributed
and quoted to einstein talking about
imagination being as important or more
important than intellect and
creativity and those types of thinking
or intuition right
so there was this process that einstein
had
where he would be
working on the math on the chalkboard or
on the paper
until he hit a diminishing return and he
just wasn't making progress
and then he would take a break and he'd
go puff his
pipe and look at the clouds and kind of
zone out
or play his violin kind of zone out
and then at a certain point in the
zoning out and i deal with pop
and then you go back with that idea to
the white board and work on it
so now i'm going to
say a metaphor for what's happening
neurologically that we don't know
is actually how neurology works but and
so i'm specifying
that this is not a absolute mechanistic
statement it's a metaphor
so that there is this
kind of left hemispheric
more serial more analytic process
and then there is a more right
hemispheric more parallel
more synthetic process and
the corpus callosum has a largely
inhibitory or shunting process between
those and that the analytic process
actually has to shut off for a little
while for the synthetic process
so the analytic is this axioms these
data these logical transforms this
because this because this therefore this
syllogistically right and the other one
is a pattern analysis of look for
everything like this
and then uh aha that seems to come out
of nowhere we might think of his
intuition but it didn't come out of
nowhere it's just
that process doesn't happen consciously
in the same way because it's actually
beyond the
bandwidth of the conscious mind
and that that then can give a new
insight but we don't take it as absolute
truth we then have to plug it back into
the other process and see how it works
but then once you hit diminishing return
there go back to this one
and i think it was wigner might have
been teller but i think it was wigner
who about the physicist the great
physicist who developed modern physics
said
we all knew that in terms of raw
horsepower von neumann was the smartest
like he could just figure out he
could do the math faster than any of us
it was obvious
but for all of his cleverness
einstein still was the one with the
deepest insights
and some reason for that it wasn't just
straight clock speed
it was something else right um
so i would say there is the study
read fact check and then also
go let yourself have that in mind don't
distract onto the laundry list or
whatever and then
meditate look at the clouds zone out and
then see what ideas come and journal
those down and then go back
right let yourself kind of have both of
those processes
and then find the facts as best you can
and then also step back and consciously
try to put them together
what kind of overarching picture
or narratives or whatever might make
sense but be careful because it might
not be a simple narrative it might be
lots of overlapping ones
right but try to see would this
overarching kind of frame make sense of
lots of these
and then say well if that was if this
narrative was true
what else would be true and go look to
see is that there or not what would
falsify or verify
this narrative or this hypothesis or
kind of overarching structural frame
um
so yeah those are some things that's
good
it's really helpful what other offerings
or
ways can people continue to engage with
you
i think you shared these there are these
couple videos we did with rebel wisdom
they called them the war on sense making
uh it was
basically we're here we're sharing tools
of sense making there we were more
sharing tools of propaganda that are
commonly used in the media landscape
that mess up your sense making to be
able to recognize them so you won't be
wrongly affected by them
the intention of those videos was to
kind of inoculate people against
um bad sense making those are worth
checking out and uh
then if if you want follow me on
facebook
i don't post public stuff very often but
i if i do i post it there
and uh podcasts and other stuff some of
it historically
is on uh civilizationemerging.com but
it's
not very updated um
facebook's probably the best place
i find that the the earnestness and the
curiosity
comes from something that you could
think of as a
spiritual impulse there is like actually
a reverence for reality that wants to
understand it
there is a respect for and uh
yeah there's a respect for the integrity
of reality and a reverence that wants
to and it's almost like if you have a
lover and you really want to love them
well
you want to know their childhood stories
and what they love in their favorite
color flower and their favorite
songs and whatever so that you can
actually love them well and it doesn't
mean that you'll ever fully know them
you shouldn't ever think that but
that you want to know them better as an
expression of the love that's there and
so and that's not the only thing you
want you don't just want to know them
you also want to
have union with them you also want to
serve them right well the same is true
with reality writ large
where you want to seek to understand it
not that you will ever understand it
completely but the desire to understand
more as a kind of
cognitive or intellectual closeness or
intimacy with reality it's a
sign of a certain respect and reverence
and love
and there's something just profoundly
beautiful
in that and it's also
and that's where it's motivated by what
you just call pure desire to know or
pure
learning but where it's motivated by the
desire to make a difference in the world
i
i would like these people not to be
dying i'd like to have a solution that
doesn't create an authoritarian state
because i care about freedoms
that then also is i want to understand
reality enough to be effective
motivated by my love for people for
nature for reality and my desire to
serve so the basis of
where the energy to do the work comes
from is actually love
and the deep the more you deepen your
love and care the more energy you will
have to do the work that it takes to
have that love and care be
active and manifest in serving that
which is
loved and cared about
that's beautiful thank you
um yeah i've been talking with a couple
people lately of like
what is the the contagion of love
you know that we can kind of match this
moment with as
so many are feeling so much fear um
and i love yeah the the idea that that
love can
get reverenced and we get you know more
and more understanding and curiosity and
um yeah it's it's kind of an antidote
to kind of like the fear and shutdown
that a lot of people are in right now
it's like
a love and yeah the curiosity and the
invitational tone of this all uh
is a really lovely antibody sort of
moment there there's a little
thing i'd like to offer here so
something a
good philosopher friend of mine shared
with me that was very profound is um
fear is not the opposite of love
fear is a reaction to love
it is sourced in it i can only be afraid
of something being harmed that i don't
want to have be harmed that i care about
and so when people are totally apathetic
ready to commit suicide don't feel fear
around dying don't feel fear around
hurting other people whatever
because there is no love or care that is
binding them still
if i and let's say i i don't feel any
fear over something being destroyed i
don't care about them like it let
it burn down
so the fear is a response to
something i love and care about where
i'm thinking about it getting harmed in
the future
i'm afraid of going crazy i it's because
i actually love
life and my own ability to be sane and
to connect and contribute and to take
care of my
family and to experience whatever it is
right like there's actually a
value a reverence on that
now the fear might be a unconscious
response i'm not consciously saying i
would like to get afraid now so it's an
unconscious response and it might be a
disempowered or disempowering response
but it still
derives its energy from the depth of
what is cared about
so i can do a conscious and empowering
response instead where i say oh i care
about this thing so
instead of focusing on automatically
unconsciously what the bad outcome is
going to be and feeling like i can't do
anything so i just get afraid
what is the good outcome i would like
and what can i do about it
so i get empowered in that so i move the
fearful to careful
full of care right and
act from there anger also comes from
love
sadness also does the apathy would just
be like it
i'm not angry not and so they might all
be unconscious
i'm not choosing to feel that they might
all be
disempowering or empowering but you can
find conscious and empowering where the
anger becomes more like passion
and the sadness becomes more like depth
of appreciation and gratitude and fear
becomes more like
carefulness and proactivity
but any of those emotions don't think of
them as bad
think of them as signals of something
that is cared about
and then trace it back to what is it
that i actually love and care about
and then what is it that i want to have
happen and how can i actually be
empowered towards it
beautiful yeah i had a realization a
couple of months ago of
instead of washing away fear seeing i
was sitting on
the side of a river um seeing it as a
stepping stone
and the other side of the river being
bravery
um i'm seeing it as yeah the logical
response but i love it
interwoven with love yeah and that
fearful
careful play on words is very evocative
thank you so much for your time and for
all of this wisdom
um yeah really looking forward to seeing
the conversation that it
incites in our trim tab trainees
and uh yeah thank you also for all of
the work that you're doing in this
moment
we appreciate you thank you for making
this series and for uh having me here
and
i'm very excited to see what comes from
the people going through all of these
and
how their sense making and solution
capacities increase and what they can do
with that
thank you